NEA/NY Audio-Visual Materials 6322 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NEA/NY Audio-Visual Materials
1989-1995
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Education Association of New York
New York Educators Association
6322 AV
1.11 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
These 33 video cassettes were collected by the NEA/NY and range in date from 1984 to 1995, though some of the videos have no date on the box or label. The videos were retained by NYSUT after the 2006 merger and transferred to the Kheel Center in 2011.
7576518
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, January 31, 2012
Biographical / Historical
The New York Education Association/New York (NYEA, later NEA/NY) was the product of the tensions between the National Education Association (NEA) and the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). Those tension at the national level were, in turn, a result of the merger of the NEA's New York State Teachers Association (NTSTA) and the AFT's United Teachers of New York (UTNY) to form the New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) in 1972. Eventually, in 1976, NYUST disaffiliated from NEA, keeping only its AFT affiliation.
In response to the disaffiliation NEA set up a rival union in New York, NEA/NY, and got some locals to leave NYSUT for the new union. This did not work as well as the NEA leadership had hoped and membership in the new union was stagnant while NYSUT grew. Finally, in 2006, a new merger brought the 35,000 NEA/NY members back into NYSUT.
Scope and Contents
Thirty-three VHS video cassettes from the 1980s and 1990s. Subjects include interviews, NEA television commercials, Delegate and Representative Assembly footage, addresses by Bill Clinton and Mario Cuomo, rallies, and NEA instructional and informational productions. One video of NEA TV spots includes some Spanish language material.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6322: NEA/NY Board of Directors Records
7576518
- NERLC 2 Cuomo (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Tape 8 Long Island (Box 1, Folder 2)
- NEA Testimonials from Summer Conf. (Beta Dub interview) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1st half of Morning. Man on Street interviews (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Wayne Central Teacher Rally, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Scope and Contents
  1/26/1990
- WNYT-TV, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  4/17/1989
- Child Lures Series - WTEN, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  May 3-21 1993
- Business Weekend - Financial News Network, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  10/19/1990
- Delegate Assembly, Buffalo, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  two tapes
- Educational Summit Meeting - A New Compact for Learning, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  9/19/1991
- Child Lures News Series: WPTZ-TV (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lobby Day - Window Dub, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Clinton's address at Cuomo Rally, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  11/3/1994
- WROC Channel 8 Rochester DA Coverage, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  5/10/1991
- North Country Review - Frinancing Educ. (WCFE-TV) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Academic Convocation & Sobol, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  10/21/1987
- Eno, Geiger Interview (Ch. 40 Binghamton), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Jan-89
- Lobby Day, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- NE Regional Leadership Conference, Buffalo, NY - Governor Mario Cuomo, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Jan-90
- NE Regional at Buffalo, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- State line: Call Governor Cuomo (Box 1, Folder 21)
- NEA Representative Assembly - Mary Hatwood Keynote address, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  7/2/1989
- Around the Tiers Teaching WBN (Box 1, Folder 23)
- What's Happenin' Productions (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Best in the Class, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- State of State (Box 1, Folder 26)
- School Days (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Make it Happen - Teach (Box 1, Folder 28)
- NEA TV Spots, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  1. Construction Worker-Compensation; 2. Wheaton - Dropout; 3. Cisneros - College Aid/Higher Ed. (Sp/En); 4. School Secretary - Esp; 5. First "B" - Teacher Competency; 6. Judge - Compensation/Class Size/Shortage; 7. Gas Station - Dropout (Spanish & English)
- White House Reception - National Education Association, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  10/11/1995
- NEA Commercials - 4 Spots, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Geography, Chemistry, Music, Home Room
- NEA State B-Roll, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)